It turns out that there are two
fundamental ways of looking at the world.
And in the modern Western
world, we've decided that one of
them is primary. And I think we
picked the wrong one. So what are
the two ways of looking at the world? You
can think about what the world is made of,
say,
you can think about that from the
perspective of experience, or as a
materialist, you can think
about what the world is made of, or you
can think about how to act in the world.
And since you're
alive, figuring out how to act in
the world is arguably of primary
importance and perhaps of
primary reality. Now, action is more
than how you navigate in the world,
moving. Let's
say because your perception is also action
predicated. So for example, when you look
at the world to find out what it is, you
have to direct your attention. And that
happens many
ways. It happens unconsciously, there's
all sorts of mechanisms in your visual
system, from your
eyes back into the neurological systems
that control vision that are moving your
eyes constantly.
When you look at something, you're not
a passive observer, you're an active
observer. There's no
without action. There's no primary sense
data about what the world is without
action. You're
locked in a framework of action, even at
the level of attention. Now, you know this
to some degree,
if you're in a restaurant, even forget
about vision. Well, if you're in a
restaurant, and
you're sitting with your guests, you pay
attention to them, perhaps the waiter and
the waitress and
not the rest of the people in the cafe,
generally speaking, unless something strange
happens.
There's many things you could look at,
but you direct your attention to what to
what's of import.
So you're focusing always on what's
relevant, and what commands
center stage. And so the
question is, what commands
center stage? And why? Now,
in order to act in the world, and
to attend to the world,
you have to find out what's relevant. And
so you direct your attention to what's of
import.
Frame your perception. And the reason you
have to frame your perception is because
there's an
indefinite number of things to attend to.
So if you were painting this wall, let's
say, if that's
a great choice, perhaps it's not. This is
very featureless wall. Although if you
attended to it
very carefully, you'd see that there were
gradations of shade and light and color.
If you're going to
be a photorealist who is attending to
anything in this room, a photorealist
painting, you'd find out
that there's an
infinite amount of detail around you.
There's an infinite amount of detail in a
face, in an array of faces, in a crowd, in
a place. You drown in detail. You have to
focus. You focus your
attention. And the question is, or a
question is, what structure do you
use to focus your attention?
To sequence the actions that underlie your
perceptions in relationship to a goal.
That's a good
way of thinking about it. So what I've
got here first is a simple frame of
perception. And it
consists of three parts. Wherever you
are, you have a sense of where you are,
right? You're
situated somewhere because you're a navigating
creature. You're headed somewhere as
well. And
then you have to strategize and organize.
You have to strategize and organize. You
have to
organize your attention and your action in
order to move you from the place you're
at to the place
that you're going. Now, the framework that
you use to evaluate your attention and
action has that structure.
So who's figured that out?
Cybernetic theorists, starting
with Norbert Weiner back in
the 1940s. He worked on missile control
systems in World War II. He was a
founder of computation.
And if you're trying to shoot down a missile,
you have a beginning place. You have a
trajectory of the
missile. You have a predicted trajectory.
You have to organize the machinery so that
it decreases the
gap between the projectile and the
target till the target is hit. That's a
cybernetic viewpoint.
Phenomenologists, phenomenologists, starting
with Husserl and then Heidegger, two
famous
philosophers. Husserl, in particular,
at least to begin with, was a
philosopher. He was a philosopher.
He was unhappy with the materialist,
reductionist, atheist view of reality.
And he hypothesized that
our fundamental sense of what was
most real had gone astray, especially
after the dawn of the
scientific revolution, with its concentration
on its insistence that the material
substructure
was the most real.
Phenomena. Phenomena means to shine forth.
It's from the Greek word phanestai.
So it means in a way
what presents itself. The burning bush in
the story of Exodus, that's a phenomena,
something
that grabs your attention, right, that
captivates you or compels you to listen or
watch or consider
or follow or imitate. That's
a phenomena. As you make your
way through the world,
things shout out to you,
command your attention and make
themselves relevant in
relationship to your
aims. So if you're planning a pleasant
interlude with a family member
and they throw a curveball into
the affair, then that
phenomenon stands forth in your
field of experience.
Rettawa went out after him and he goes,
all right, so what are we going to do?
All right, he takes a backing was a strong
bath, green lukewarm, amodern birch naked
husband buy some cookie. But then
it shows how deeply regrettin g
of my life has literally
captured what really
happened to me, and it shows what I felt
about myself, what I was going through.
All right, so it's life.
And what is it rather lost?
Moving towards the goal. Negative emotion
indicates that something has gone astray.
You can think
about the cybernetic system that I described
earlier. The anti -missile missile is
unhappy as
it deviates from the course, right? Your
emotions are trajectory adjustment systems.
Positive
indicates forward movement and validates
the frame of perception. And negative
emotion indicates
deviation from the path or failure of the
frame. Okay, so keep that in mind. Now,
cybernetics,
phenomenology. Perceptual
psychologists began to sort this out
in the 20th century as well,
not least with the observation that
there was no perception independent
of action, right?
That imagine that you're blind
and you're using your fingers,
to put together a composite
sensory picture of someone's face.
That's exactly what you do with
your eyes. Spot, spot, spot, spot, spot,
composite. And there's a foreground that's
fovea dependent.
The fovea is the center point of your eye.
It's the high resolution part of your
vision. It
requires much more neurological processing
than the periphery. If your entire retina
was fovea,
you'd need a cortex that was many times
larger to process it. You maximize the use
of available
neurological resource by
pinpointing the fovea and
intensely concentrating on
the particular point of
interest around your fovea, which is very
high resolution. The world becomes lower
and lower
and lower resolution until out here you're
seeing in black and white. And back here,
there's no
nothing, not even the sense of absence,
right? So center point focus on what's
relevant and
important in relationship to a goal surrounded
by a periphery that disappears into,
into what?
Into you could say the void. If you're using
poetic terminology, that'll be relevant
as we
start to understand the structure of
stories. That's a cybernetic frame. It's a
phenomenological frame. Now the phenomenologists,
Husserl and Heidegger redefined
reality itself. And the reason they were
doing that, there were two reasons. They
were concerned
that the divide between object and subject
that had been set up as a consequence of
the scientific
and enlightenment revolution prioritized
the objective and left the subjective
in a, what would
you say? In an abyss of uncertainty and
meaninglessness in part, because it was
defined away.
The subjective became epiphenomenological.
In fact, even the's being a more
fundamental reality, with the
fundamental reality. or the more fundamental
reality now that's an existential
problem because we can't live in
a universe that's devoid of all
meaning but suffering. Let's say,
and it's Perverse because there's no
perception without a subjective observer,
and if you contemplate the situation
scientifically, even let's say the basic
sense of the universe itself, the bottom
and bottom, the fundamental truth
of the universe, of the instinct.
Sense data that the empiricists believe
that the world is made of is dependent for
its existence
on perception and perception is dependent
on action and action is dependent on goal
and goal is dependent on value and so
the notion that there's some objective
substrat of existence
in the absence of a perceiver who's
embedded in a world of value and meaning is
not tenable
even from the scientific perspective
partly because we know that perception is
action predicated now the phenomenologists
tried to solve that subject object
divide problem
and the nihilism or valuelessness
that emerges in the scientific
world view by prioritizing
not objective reality but
experience as such so
you're sitting in this lecture
lecture theater you're you have a focus of
attention that's why it's a theater it's
built
to hint to you when you
make your entrance how
you're supposed to conduct
yourself the chairs
are all facing in a particular direction
they converge on a point the point is the
point of
the lecture the point is the point of your
attention the point is the goal of your
attention right that all organizes your
perceptions it foregrounds some things
at least in principle
when you're not thinking or distracted what
i'm saying or the slides that i'm using
and that renders everything
else increasingly
irrelevant as it diverges
from the central point
and so there's a foreground and generally
when you're interacting with someone the
foreground of your attention
is their face, and even more specifically,
their eyes, and even more specifically,
their pupils.
And you do that so you can see what they're
pointing to, because you can tell what
they're
interested in. You can tell what they're
compelled by. You can read emotions through
the eyes. Our
eyes are adapted. Evolution. Evolution has
adapted our eyes to make them maximally
visible. Colored
black against a white background, so that
when we interact with people, we can see
what their point
is. Having seen their point, we can inhabit
their frame of reference. We can infer
what's meaningful
to them. We can adopt their emotions. We
can mimic those emotions on our own body,
and that's how we
understand them. Our face is a value
display system, right? And when you're
concentrating on someone, you
almost always look at their eyes.
We're very, very good at that.
Even from a distance, you can detect
small deviations in someone's eye gaze
direction,
because understanding the object of their
intention and attention is the most
important
thing you can derive. You're focused here
on what I'm saying. You're watching my
face. You're
watching my eyes. The world constructs
itself around that. Husserl's fundamental
point was that
all perception,
is intentional. It's associated with a
goal. It moves towards a point, and that
point is related
to the insistence that I put
forward at the beginning, that
our perception is action -oriented,
that our problem is navigation. How do we
get from point A to point B, from what is
currently to
what should be? We're always,
somewhere, moving somewhere else. And then
there's a gradient, which is why in this
diagram,
there's a slant upward. What's the gradient?
Well, if you're aiming up, the gradient
is upward.
The gradient is uphill. The gradient is
from a lesser place to a greater place. Why
would you
move from what is to what should be if the
place you're headed to wasn't better than
the place you're at?
After, are you currently hungry? Right?
Is your goal to achieve
something ineminable?
Yeah,
good,
entrepot. We're now at a kg,
going 255 yards, before I realize
what's going on between times is
energy expenditure problem. You want to
foreground a goal that's valuable in
relationship to where
you are, that doesn't require more energy
than you have at hand. Now, you can
sequence goals,
and we'll get to that. Okay,
what's this frame? It's a
cybernetic frame. So, cybernetic pioneers
and many of the developers of
computational systems, especially the
robotics engineers who started to
understand that you couldn't do robotics
computation without
embodiment. The phenomenologists,
the psychologists of perception
have all converged
on a notion that we inhabit a frame of
perception that organizes the world around
us,
that has a goal in mind. The last thing you
need to know about that to begin with is
that's the
story. That's a story. So, the
postmodernists insisted that
we inhabit a story. They dispensed
with the notion that there was a central
unifying story that was common to all
places and all times,
let's say, but they insisted, and
correctly so, that even the scientific
enterprises,
is nested inside a story. What's the
scientific story? We're making things better.
Otherwise,
it's an evil scientist's story, and there's
plenty of them too, and we might say
that the true science
is the science that serves what? Mankind,
the good of mankind, and it's an upward
journey, and that's
not built into the scientific enterprise
itself. It's the a priori frame that the
scientist has to
inhabit so that they aren't a threat.
Right. That's the case, you could say, for
everything that you do. If any of your
actions
are predicated on an ultimately downward
aim, then you're an agent of chaos, right?
At minimum.
A story. What's a story? A story is a
description of a frame of perception.
Now, think about this.
When you go to a movie, think about what
you're doing. So, you see a sequence of
subplots,
and in the subplots, you see the characters
in motion. You see them directing their
attention.
You infer their goals from their speech
and their patterns of action. You put that
together as a
pastiche across multiple instances, and
you draw your conclusions about the aim
and direction of the character. Having done
that, you can adopt that frame. Having
adopted the frame,
you see the world through the perspective
of the protagonist, and you experience it.
Experience his or her emotions,
right? You do that to experiment with
a frame of perception
with no risk, right? Some
emotional risk. There's enough
enthusiastic impetus in the imitation
so that even if you're watching a horror
movie that would expose you to phenomena
that normally
would be aversive, placing yourself in the
fictional frame and experimenting with
the
exposure is sufficiently motivating in the
positive direction so
that you'll pay for the
privilege, right? Why is fiction so
important? Why are we so compelled
by stories? Because a story
is a description of the manner in which we
frame our perception, our attention, and
our action.
So there's a viewpoint,
that makes the story not
secondary, not laid upon another
more fundamental reality, but
a priori. Now, there's obviously an
interplay that has to occur between
our understanding of
how the world is constituted and how we
should act in it. But the notion that
there's a simple primacy of
material being seems, at
minimum,
seems half true and rife
with conceptual flaws.
The simplest frame, the simplest story,
you ask a toddler, a kindergartner, what
did you do today? I went to school with
mom.
Started at home, I went to school, that was
the sequence. I went to school with mom
and on the way
a scary dog jumped at the fence and barked
and I got afraid and we thought about
going home, but we decided
not to and we continued.
That's a little hero story. That's a disruption
of the frame by an unexpected event.
And then
it's reconfiguration, even at a higher
level, because the kindergartner in that
instance,
in principle, discovers a courage to move
forward into the unknown that he didn't
know he had. Right. That's a
micro hero narrative. And we'll,
that's a variation on the basic
frame.
The simplest story is I was here, I went
there and this is how I did it. A more
complex story is I was here, I was going
there and the bottom fell out. And then I
went somewhere else and put myself back
together and I got a new frame and away I
went. Right. And that's, that's a story
about how a story transforms. That's a
meta story. And most great, all
great stories are meta stories.
Okay, so here's a more
behaviorist version of the
same idea of frame. What is
subtitled the unbearable present? Why?
Because now isn't good enough. Because if it
was, you wouldn't be doing anything. You're
always, this is the phenomenological,
the philosophers, the phenomenal
logical insistence that your experience
of the world is pitched always
to the other side of the frame.
It is the goal of your attention and
action, that that imbues the frame of your
experience with significance. You can
imagine sitting not doing anything.
Imagining, which is a form of action,
running variant possibilities through your
mind, experimenting with a sequence of
different aims, evaluating the manner in
which the emotional landscape
shifts as you portray it.
Different fictional outcomes in
an attempt to experiment with
determining what course you
should chart before you implement it in the
real world. That's a dream. That's what
dreams do.
The more radical and improbable and
incomprehensible dreams shift the
elements of your
framework of perception so dramatically
that you can't necessarily explicitly
understand the transformation. We'll talk
more about that. You start at what is
with its insufficiency. You
move towards what should be. That's
the value proposition. Why expend
energy if the goal
doesn't have value? If you expend energy
towards goals that have no value,
you die. Right, right. Honeybees, when
they go out and find a flower bed,
they come back and they
signal to the other bees the navigation
pathway to the flower bed, indicating
by their level of
enthusiastic movement, the richness of
the store of value. That's exactly what
people do when they
get excited when they tell you a story.
They signal by their willingness to expend
energy in the telling.
That the destination is worth the
effort, right? That's a stable means of
representing value,
treasure, all the way from insects to human
beings, right? So if you see a speaker
who's
pouring out energy in the exposition of
their story, then you understand that they
believe that
the destination is worth the investment
of energy. And that's compelling to you
because your proposition
would be, what? How could he?
Possibly continue to expend energy if the
destination wasn't of sufficient value,
right?
Right. So that's why enthusiasm, which is
positive emotion, and also the state of
being possessed by
the divine entheos is enthusiastic,
right? Which would imply that
the ultimate goal is the goal
that fills you with enthusiasm, right? Which
is a way actually of determining within
the confines of
your own framework of experience,
what it is that has intrinsic meaning
to you. Because if you
posit a goal, you see a goal, a possible
future, and you frame your perception in a
manner that
produces no forward moving impulse, which
is positive emotion, then you have no
heart
for the adventure. And so one of the ways
that you investigate the structure of your
own psyche,
or your own unconscious, or your own
being, or being itself, is by evaluating
frames that switch
goals until your emotions signify
to you that the pathway is
worth walking down. Now,
it's more complicated than mere acquisition.
There's going to be some risk along the
way,
which you want. You want that risk because
you're not going to be able to walk down
that path. You're
going to be able to find your own path.
And so one of the things that you're going
to experience
is the same as you're going to experience.
You're going to experience the kind of
want to pick a goal that not only provides
you with something that you recognize
deeply as significant,
but that transforms you as you pursue
it so that your capability to posit
and pursue better goals increases.
It's the same thing. You want it
easy. You don't want it impossible.
You want it challenging. You want it
adventurous. You want it difficult. How
difficult? That's the main thing. You want
it difficult. And that's the
nature of the game after all.
That's what you're to determine, as difficult
as possible while maintaining maximal
enthusiasm.
That's what children do when they play.
That's what you do when you're playing.
That's what you do when
you engage in a game.
If you're proficient at
generating frames of play or
story, then you maximize
enthusiasm and developmental
transformation simultaneously.
Right. That's a good deal.
That means that you're playing a game
that's worthwhile, that gets better as you
play it.
Right. That's an upward.
That's a Jacob's ladder, by the way.
That's a stairway to heaven.
Right. Exactly.
A spiral upward that moves into the
ineffable good that communicates
with the earth, that lays
out a pathway upward.
And your nervous system itself is tuned.
This is an indication of the
fundamental reality of these frames.
Your nervous system itself is
tuned so that what you experience.
Within that frame of reference, when it's
optimized, is meaningful motivation.
Right. Now, let's think
about this scientifically.
How would have you evolved the
capacity to specify a pathway forward
emotionally and motivationally, so
biologically, if that wasn't real?
Right. If reality is what selects from
among the variations that compose life.
And reality has selected us to have an
experience of deep meaning, when we encounter
the pathway that leads us upward and
transforms us, how is that not real?
Right.
Simple story. I was here.
I did this. What is,
what does it mean to do?
It means fundamentally to move, right?
That's where words, that's
where the rubber hits the road.
Words make their embodiment in action.
And so you can set a frame
abstractly, but you act it out.
And when you're acting it out,
it's not abstract anymore, right?
Because this is a solution in
part to the mind-body problem.
You can formulate the frame and the goal
abstractly, but when you implement it,
you're moving.
The movement, that's not abstract.
So consciousness, abstracted
consciousness, grounds itself in embodied.
The movement, that's the incarnation
of the spirit in the corporeal world.
That's a way to think about it
poetically or religiously, right?
You take your abstract conception of the
good, or depending on what you're pursuing,
and you bring that down.
And that's the breath of
the spirit by God into man.
That's a symbolic representation of
that, or the idea of incarnation.
That's the same thing.
This, your goal, your frame is.
An active agent.
You could think about it as a spirit.
You bring that spirit down
to earth and embody it.
And that's how consciousness
transforms itself into action, right?
You can infer the abstracted goal of a
character by watching their action, right?
What's he up to?
I'll watch him and see.
I'll see how he directs his attention.
I'll see towards what he
moves or what he avoids.
Right? What's he up to?
Or what he thinks is relevant and
what he thinks is irrelevant.
I'll infer the frame.
You do this to yourself, by the way,
and this is something to understand.
You have proximal knowledge only
of your frame of reference.
You're here today, for example.
So you deem that valuable.
You put in the time and
effort to come here.
But why?
Why are you here?
And then you could tell me and I could
ask, well, why is that important to you?
And you could tell me that and I could
ask, why is that important to you?
And that will make a chain up to where you
don't know how to answer the question.
And that's where your conscious knowledge
of your own aims and motivational
structure disappear.
The psychoanalysts would
say into the unconscious.
It's into the implicit, right?
And we'll describe how
that works as we progress.
How is the frame?
Framed?
Well, psychologists study perception,
attention, emotion, cognition,
motivation.
Psychologists had a proclivity to
describe motivations as drives.
And drive theory came
from the behaviorists.
The behaviorists believed that, attempted
to demonstrate that our actions and the
actions of animals were deterministic,
changeable.
And that was the response they received.
If you put your hand on a hot
stove, you'll jerk it back.
There's a feedback loop from your sensory
nerves to the spine to your motor nerves.
It's very fast because it's short.
And if you encounter a particular noxious
stimuli, one that would damage the
receptive surfaces,
that's a good definition of noxious.
Then you'll withdraw, which is an action,
obviously, in the absence of any conscious
intent. And extremely rapidly.
The behaviorists tried to generate
a model of motivation that chained
reflexes together in increasingly complex
manners to account for the kind of
sophisticated behavior that animals
were capable of, but ultimately failed.
B .F. Skinner, who was an outstanding
behaviorist, he trained pigeons
to direct guided missiles
using photographs.
And he essentially did that using a process
that looked, in a sense, like reflex
chaining.
If he was going to train a rat to climb a
little ladder and then maybe walk across
like another ladder that was horizontal
and then down, he'd make the rats hungry
first.
He starved his laboratory animals to 75 %
of their normal weight so that they were
maximally motivated by food.
Then he would watch them.
And when they moved around the cage and got
close to the ladder, the base, he'd give
them a food pallet.
Then they'd start hanging around
the bottom of the ladder.
Now and then, they put a paw up.
Then he'd give them another food pallet.
And pretty soon, they were doing this.
And then he could get them to climb up the
ladder and to dance on top and to go down
the other side.
Behaviorists trained rats
to run down runways.
Let's call that reflex chaining.
But then some smart behaviorists, and I
don't remember who it was, tied the bags.
Legs of a rat up and put it on a cart,
and it managed to go down the maze runway
with no
problem, even though it had never
encountered that particular problem before.
Animals, human
beings with sufficiently complex nervous
systems, interact with the world in a
manner that can't be
accounted for by mere
deterministic reflex chaining.
Motivations are not drives. It's
complicated, and I'll see if I can unpack
it. What a motivation, hunger is a
motivation, thirst is a
motivation. You can think about a motivation
as independent as an emotion from an
emotion. There's
overlap because emotion and motivation
aren't exactly scientific categories right
there,
folk categories. But for the purposes of
our discussion, we'll define a motivation
as an instinctual goal.
That's a better way of
thinking about it. So
you're hungry. Okay, you're
working at home, and you start to become
hungry. You notice. How do you notice?
Because a new story
pops into your head. What's the story?
It would be a good idea to go into the
kitchen and find
something to eat in the fridge, right?
And then that, as you become more hungry,
that becomes more insistent.
It attempts to...
Take a grip of the perceptual structure
within which you frame your attention, your
action,
and your emotions. You start thinking, it
would be a good idea to go get something
to eat. That's
a tag of positive emotion. It's starting
to become... My hunger is starting to
become unpleasant,
right? So you can see there's a competition
between the frame of reference that
you're using,
let's say, to organize your work and this
emergent motivational state. At some
point, things switch,
are you in a deterministic state then? No,
you're navigating under the influence of
a biological
system whose goal is to satiate
your hunger. Okay, is that
deterministic? It has deterministic
elements. You know, the more ancient a
motivational system is, the more it's
associated
with behavioral patterns that are, if not
instinctual, at least very easy to learn.
Right, so you can imagine that the longer
across evolutionary history a motivational
state has
existed, pain for example, the more it
comes equipped with a panoply of relatively
at -hand
behavioral and attentional mechanisms that
it can put into play when it grips you.
A toddler is a sequence of motivational
states, an unintegrated sequence of
motivational states.
What are some motivational states?
Hunger, thirst, sexual
excitation, pain, play.
Those are some of the
basic motivational states.
Exploration, defensive rage, although anger
is also arguably an emotion because you
can feel it
in relationship to a goal, but it can also
signify a target. That's why motivations
and emotions
aren't exactly a clean category. You
know, the older and more profound the
motivation, the more
ancient the neurological system that
mediates it. Many of the fundamental
motivational states
that set goals are hypothalamic. The
hypothalamus is a brain area that sits on top
of the spinal cord
and provides the first order
abstract integration of increasingly
complex spinal reflexes.
The hypothalamus mediates hunger, thirst,
temperature, excretion, defensive
aggression. That's one half that the
other half mediates exploration.
The hypothalamic system that mediates
exploration is the root of the dopaminergic
system.
The dopaminergic system is the biochemical
system that underlies positive emotion in
relationship to a goal.
That's how old it is. That's how old
exploration is. Pain is in its own little world
as is anxiety. This is the
carriers of depression.
Those are also very primordial brain systems
but they're not hypothalamic so this
frame of perception is susceptible
to grip by motivational
forces and it's useful
the frame it's a cybernetic frame
it's a phenomenological frame it's a
perceptual
frame it's a story it's also a spirit or
personality okay it's all of those things
at the same time think about what you're
like when you're angry right that's it's a
complex
system it's simplified compared to what
you're like in a state where you're not
dominated by a
singular motivation but you have many
options at hand when you're angry right and
the world takes
on a particular kind of phenomenological
reality when you're angry things tilt very
much in the negative direction for example
if you're arguing with someone that you
hypothetically love almost
everything that will come to you is going
to be the same thing you're going to have
to do
when you're angry is negative right and all
the things that you might hope to enjoy
in a playful
manner with them disappear in favor
of dominance and defeat right the
motivational state that grips
your goal makes everything that interferes
with it irrelevant including your
memories and maybe
you'll snap out of that hopefully and
you'll think what the hell possessed me and
that's a useful
question Nietzsche after he
announced that god had died in the
1850s suggested that the consequence
of that high order
disintegration would be roughly
threefold descent into
nihilism it's a kind of
fragmentation proclivity to move to
alternate totalizing belief systems ideology
he was
particularly concerned with potentially
the rise of nationalism but also with
what eventually became communism, right?
Or he thought we could
create our own values.
The psychoanalyst came along and said,
what makes you so sure you
can create your own values?
You're not even the master
in your own house, right?
So you can think about yourself cycling
through a sequence of possessions, right?
That's very useful to ask yourself,
just what is the nature of
this spirit that possesses me?
And you can reduce it
to a biological drive,
but motivations aren't drives.
They're sub-personalities.
And they have not only a
viewpoint in terms of goal,
in terms of how the world lays itself out,
the whole phenomenological
field, the story.
They also have a history,
social and biological.
And they have a, what would you say?
They have a mythic nature.
Many archaic gods, Ares, Eros,
are personifications of
motivational states.
Ares being, for example, the god of war.
And so just like real world mobsters
are said to act like Hollywood
mobsters,
you, when you're angry,
imitate the culturally
patterned personality of anger
that has called out to you to imitate
in the course of your life.
And that's what possesses.
You a constellation of possession
by negative motivational states.
You could think of something that's
approximating the demonic, right, right.
It's very useful to know that
these things are alive with will.
Every drive attempts to
philosophize in its spirit.
That's Nietzsche, right?
Very smart.
So it's not, I'm not
angry in a driven way.
I'm angry in an entire world
constructing manner, right?
It.
Transforms my perceptions.
It transforms my goals, transforms
my patterns of attention.
It changes my memories.
It brings different
words to the forefront.
fantasies to the forefront.
It lays out an entirely different
world of options in front of me.
And God only knows what it is at its base.
Right? So the psychoanalysts came along,
especially Jung, but Freud to begin
with, who noted our id,
he was the formulator of
the concept of id, right?
That panoply of biological drives drives
Freud concentrated most on sex and
aggression
that had their proclivity to have their
way with us rather than the reverse,
right? And so can we
create our own values?
Try it and see.
So that was Eve's temptation, which is a
story we'll get back to right in the garden
of Eden. Right?
God tells man and woman
that they have full freedom
to explore and use,
except they're forbidden to incorporate the
fruit of the knowledge of good and evil,
right?
The fruit of the knowledge of good and
evil is the essence of the world of value.
Eve falls prey to the temptation
to make herself like God,
by creating the world of
value that surrounds her.
And as that story was elaborated
across the centuries,
the spirit that tempted Eve to
rebel against the intrinsic
moral order and to establish her own
was associated with Lucifer,
who's the spirit of the overweening
and prideful intellect,
whose fundamental motivation,
is to usurp, right?
Follow the moral order.
Find the moral order.
Abide by the moral order.
Do not create the moral order, right?
That's the fall.
Pride goes before a fall.
The fall, garden, chaos,
reintegration.
That's the biblical story.
That's a meta-narrative.
That's a hero story.
That's a story about how a frame
collapses and transforms, right?
Those are the stories that
compel us most particularly,
as we not only encounter obstacles
to our goal-directed pursuit,
we encounter obstacles that are so profound
that they force us to transform our
pursuit, right?
So, and out of that failure, you might
say, which is not only a failure of
strategy, but a failure of frame,
growth can make itself manifest.
Death can make itself manifest,
but so can growth.
Then the question is,
how do you avoid the transformations
that culminate in death
and invite the transformations
that culminate
in growth?
And how do you conceptualize
your meta-strategy
so that that's your highest value?
That's a good way of thinking about it.
What should you pursue?
How about a pathway that improves the
probability that you will properly specify
what you pursue?
That's wisdom, right?
There's a way of doing things, right?
So no matter what you
attempt in your life,
you know, if you push yourself while you're
doing it so that you're challenged in an
adventurous way,
then you put yourself on
the edge of development
and you facilitate it.
You facilitate your vision and you
increase the capacity of your intent,
right?
And that's signified, once again,
that's signified as you would expect
by a sense of deep intrinsic meaning.
How could it be that the
meaning that orients us
could be anything but aligned with the
process that compels us or invites us
to develop?
What sort of creatures would we be
if our
deepest instinct for enthusiastic
orientation wasn't in line
with the pattern that
made us more than we are?
We just fail.
So one of the advantages of
the phenomenological view,
the cybernetic view, the narrative view,
is that it makes what matters
rather than matter primary.
Right, right.
Husserl.
The world you inhabit is
constituted by your goal.
The world you inhabit, the world
of experience that you inhabit,
that's now Heidegger.
After Husserl, Heidegger decided that if
the world of experience was intentional
and there was no,
there was nothing more primary
than the world of experience
as it makes itself
manifest in consciousness,
that's your experience,
then there was no difference
between experience
and being itself.
And that was Heidegger's
transformation of Husserl's thought.
So being in the manner that
we're going to use it is being,
is necessarily being towards an aim.
The question then arises,
what's the proper aim?
The word sin,
which is hamartia in Greek,
means to miss the target,
to miss the aim.
It's misaligned aim.
If the world
is making itself manifest to you
in a manner that's unacceptable
with regards to the reality of the
meaning that you're experiencing,
then perhaps your aim
is misaligned, right?
Then you confess that, right?
You repent and you atone, atone at one.
You replace the misaligned
aim with something higher.
Right? That's the developmental pathway.
I slipped off.
Where did I make it? I made a mistake.
Where did I make it?
How can I rectify it?
How can I use what I learned
when I investigated my error
to reconstitute my aim so that
the misalignment vanishes?
Implying that there is an aim
that's not misaligned, right?
That's partly what we're
going to investigate.
Is, how might you define an
aim that's not misaligned?
How would you put aims in sequence?
How would you hierarchically arrange them?
How would you construct
a set of frames, right?
That extend optimally
upward in a manner that
improves as you implement them.
More to that. That incorporates
the future, your future.
That incorporates other people, right?
In some harmony, right?
So that you're not at odds with your
future self or with the other people
that you're cursed and
fortunate to spend time with.
The psychophysiologists of
motivation broke fundamental
motivations into two rough categories.
Self-maintenance, thermoregulation,
thirst, hunger elimination,
and self-propagation, affiliative
desire, because we're social beings,
we have a desire.
It's just a way of categorizing these
underlying, what would you say?
It's like a society of subordinate,
sometimes superordinate
personalities that have to be
organized into a wise council
and put in their proper place
so that you can move forward in a manner
that's upward, sustainable, and social,
right? Very tight set of
constraints, very tight.
Nothing arbitrary about it.
Nothing relativistic about it.
There's very few parameters that, there are
very few solutions that fit that set of
parameters, right?
Has to work for you so that you thrive,
has to work for you so that you thrive now
and in the medium run and in the long run.
It has to work for you now so that it
works with the other people around you
so they thrive in the medium to long run.
So you all do that together so that it
improves, so that you're enthusiastic,
so that your negative emotions
are properly regulated, right?
A very tight set of constraints.
Children attain that according to Jean
Piaget when they're playing, right?
So that's a good thing to know
with regard to your life.
If you're doing something right,
you're playing, right, right.
Fragile motivational state, an
integrated motivational state,
but one that signals the
proper element of integration.
And I already defined proper.
For people who are thinking
relativistically, right?
Has to sustain itself medium to long run.
That's life eternal. By the way,
it has to improve as you play it.
It has to incorporate other people, right?
Hard. That's a hard set
of constraints to manage.
That's what I think music models, by the
way, that harmonious interplay of multiple
patterns, right?
Think about people dancing to music.
You have the patterns that
are laying themselves out.
They're all harmoniously integrated.
They're all moving towards an end.
Everybody is aligning
themselves with the harmony of
multiplicity that the music represents.
And that's a play.
That's why we play music.
Okay. Back to the basic frame, the
basic story, the ground of experience,
the phenomenological reality,
the cybernetic frame,
and the manner in which we
structure our perception.
I'm going to elaborate on
the nature of the frame.
Okay, so that you can see what the
constituent elements of the world are.
And we'll start on the surface.
We're doing the same thing in the domain
of experience that the materialist did
in the material world when they took things
apart to find out what they were made of
at their micro levels.
While your experience has layers, right?
It has depths and it has elements.
And one of the things that
the phenomenologists did,
the psychologists of perception, was
to attempt to define the affordances,
the relevant objects, rather
than merely the objects,
the relevant objects of
your experiential world.
That's the basic frame.
Point A, point B, the strategy
for movement forward.
It grounds out in action, right?
So it's not an infinite regress.
Right? So that's a good thing to know.
It stops being abstract when you act.
So then your action is the
indication of what you believe.
That's the basic frame.
What is, what should be.
That's the basic story when
you describe it, right?
The frame isn't a story.
The story is the description of a frame.
Right, right.
Okay. So what do you see when you're
moving from point A to point B?
We know this, by the way, almost.
I'm doing my best to tell you things
that I know are valid from a narrative
and a mythological perspective
and from a scientific
perspective simultaneously.
Okay. So part of what I'm drawing on here
with this particular image is work done
by a man named JJ Gibson,
who wrote a book called
An Ecological Approach
to Visual Perception.
Okay. He never defined himself as a
phenomenologist or a cyberneticist,
but it doesn't matter because
the thinking is isomorphic.
And so, and his insights, especially
with relationship to emotion,
were elaborated by a
neuropsychologist named Jeffrey Gray,
another one named Jaak
Panksepp, who were the greatest
neuropsychologists of the last half
of the 20th century, by a lot.
Gray integrated 1800 scientific
papers into his book.
It's about a six month read this
book because you have to master.
Psychopharmacology.
Brain anatomy, behavioral literature
and cybernetics to understand it.
That's a hell of a task for
one book, but it's deadly.
It's a deadly book.
And Jaak Panksepp, both of these men
knew a lot about animal experimentation
and the animal experimentalists who
were behaviorists had a oversimplified,
higher order framework of interpretation.
But man, they were good at nailing down
the details of behavior and perception.
And, and aligning that with what
we know about neurochemistry.
That's all been quite nicely integrated.
And so what I'm going to provide you with
in the next few slides is all informed
by that massive corpus of work.
Okay.
When you see, when you perceive, you
do that in relationship to your aim.
However, momentary, that's,
let's say, point B.
How do you get from point A to point B?
How did I get from point A to point B?
The story, the framework of my perception.
Okay.
If I want to walk to the chairs that
are behind you, you people are now
obstacles,
right? You've switched your reality.
And if I'm impelled by
emergency to beeline
to a destination immediately behind you,
you're in my way, right?
You're an obstacle.
You're targeted. You're
filled with negative emotion.
You know that when you curse
someone, when you drive, right?
Everyone does that.
And why?
Because you experience emotion
in relationship to a goal.
And so, and you do that in a pretty
simple and heuristic manner.
If you're busily going somewhere and an
old lady with a walker crosses the street,
that's annoying.
And you might think, well, what
the hell is wrong with you?
Which is a good question.
But the brute reality of the situation
is that if it's in your way,
it causes negative emotion, right?
If you can use it to move yourself forward,
then it produces positive emotion.
So your emotions are calibrating systems
like the error detection mechanisms on a
cybernetic system.
That tell you when you're on track
and moving towards the goal.
And when you're deviating.
That's a good way of thinking
about how emotions work.
And that also describes to some
degree the danger of them.
Because if you're operating in a narrow
frame of reference, something immediate,
you can subordinate hierarchy.
I shouldn't treat you like
an obstacle no matter what.
Well, no matter what, if I'm rushing
to the hospital to save my child.
Are you an obstacle?
Well, that's a more.
Moral question, isn't it?
No. How do you balance the
realization of someone else as
valuable in relationship
to a higher order goal when you're pursuing
a lower order goal where they're an
impediment?
To understand that, we'll have to
understand how stories are nested,
which is something we
haven't yet discussed.
What do you see in the world?
This is so cool.
So how does the world
make itself manifest?
Phenomenologically, aim first,
target destination, right?
Remember, we're hunting animals.
We exist on a throwing platform, right?
And that's age old.
That's been the case
since we were bipedal.
And so we're great at targeting.
We're great at cybernetic minimization of
distance between the present reality and
the goal.
And our emotions arrange
themselves around that, right?
And so what do you see phenomenologically?
Pathways.
That's the first thing.
That's the story tale.
That's the Golden Road.
That's the Wizard of Oz.
That's the adventure.
That's the journey of the troop
of the Lord of the Rings, right?
That's the pathway forward.
So this is a good thing to think about.
It's like, what do you have to aim
at so that the pathway forward
beckons?
So this is how you consort with your soul.
You ask yourself, what
do I have to aim at?
So the pathway forward beckons, right?
This is a negotiation, a
dialectical negotiation.
Remember in the Pinocchio movie, when
Pinocchio's conscience first shows up, right?
Jiminy Cricket, JC, Jesus Christ, right?
Jiminy Cricket was southern US
slang for Jesus Christ, JC.
Why would JC be a bug?
Because some things bug you.
They get under your skin, right?
They irritate in a direction and you can
ignore that and you can suppress it,
which is what Jonah did before he
ended up in the belly of the whale.
Like Geppetto, by the way, you can suppress
that or you can engage in a dialectic.
In the Pinocchio movie, Pinocchio engages
in a dialectic with Jiminy Cricket.
He starts out the cricket as a tramp.
With no home.
And the first advice he gives
is cliched and sloganeering.
Slogan from the Welsh, sluag
gherm, battle cry of the dead.
When Jiminy Cricket
shows up, he's generic.
He's like an overbearing superego.
He's not attuned to the specific realities
of the time and place that the puppet
who wishes to be free inhabits.
He brings a collection of
tried and true homilies
that are shallow in
consequence of their overuse
to the initial dialogue.
But the puppet persona possessed, pulled
by spring strings that aren't
under his control and not real,
engages in a dialogue with the
conscience and both transform.
At the end of the movie, Pinocchio
realizes himself and the
cricket ends up in a tuxedo
replacing his tramp clothing.
And he wears a star that's 24 karat
gold that reflects the stars.